http://www.baus.org.uk/patients/surgical_outcomes/privacy_notice_for_baus_audits.aspx

This site uses cookies to bring you the best experience. Find out more
My Links
Use this area to add quick shortcuts to your favourite pages.
Add this page
Skip to main content
MENU
Home PatientsCOVID-19: Information for Patients Find a Surgeon General Information General Information
Find general information about Urology here...
Cancer Paediatrics Stone Disease Patient Advisory Section Glossary "I think I might have..." "I think I might have..."
Find out more about urological conditions:
Blood in the semen (haematospermia) Blood in the urine (haematuria) Erectile dysfunction (impotence) Fertility problems Incontinence of urine Kidney stones Male menopause (androgen deficiency in the ageing male) Premature ejaculation Prostate symptoms (bladder outlet obstruction) Raised PSA Testicle missing Testicular lump Tight foreskin (phimosis) Urinary infection (adult) Urinary infection (child) "I'm told I need..." Patient Information Leaflets
Use the links below to find information relating to various urological procedures.
Bladder Procedures Fertility & Infertility Procedures Kidney & Adrenal Procedures Miscellaneous Procedures Penis Procedures Prostate Procedures Retroperitoneum Procedures Stone Procedures Testis & Scrotal Procedures Transplantation & Dialysis Procedures Ureter Procedures Urethra Procedures Surgical Outcomes Audits Surgical Outcomes Audits
BAUS Consultant Outcomes Publications
Interpretation of the Data Understanding the Graphs How We Do Risk Analysis Grading of Surgical Complications Privacy Notice for BAUS Audits Cystectomy Nephrectomy Percutaneous Nephrolithotomy (PCNL) Radical Prostatectomy Stress Urinary Incontinence Urethroplasty Vaginal Mesh Complications Your Patient Journey ProfessionalsBAUS Business BAUS Business
Updates, publications and recent media releases
Data & Audit Programme Elections Medals & Awards Media Gallery News President's Briefings Publications Education & Training Education & Training
The centre for BAUS urological trainees, students and educational material.
Career Path of a Urologist Continuing Professional Development (CPD) Education Committee E-Learning Revalidation Specialist Advisory Committee (SAC) Events Events Calendar
See upcoming events:
All Events Submit an Event Regions Regions
Regional information and contacts
East Midlands East of England Irish Republic Kent, Surrey & Sussex London North London South North East North West Northern Ireland Scotland East Scotland West South Central South West Wales West Midlands Yorkshire & Humber Specialist Sections Specialist Sections
As part of BAUS membership, registered members may join Urolink and up to three other sections which are relevant to their particular areas of practice.
Andrology and Genito-Urethral Surgery Endourology Female, Neurological and Urodynamic Urology Foundation Year (FY) & Core Trainee (CT) Doctors Medical Students Oncology Specialist Trainees (BSoT) Urolink Urolink
Representing BAUS in the developing world
About Urolink Contact Urolink Current Link Centres Executive Committee Faculty Membership FAQs About Urolink Funding Opportunities Overseas Urologists in the UK Photo Gallery Publications & Social Media UK Urologists Working Abroad Visit Details & Reports AboutContact Us Coronavirus & COVID-19 Find Us (or Hire a Room) Governance & Trustees Governance
The Trustees have legal and fiduciary responsibility for the Association.
Annual General Meetings BAUS Council Members Equality Statement Trustees Trustees' Annual Report History of BAUS Joining BAUS Joining BAUS
Membership of BAUS is open to any medical practitioner in urological practice interested in promoting the objects or the organisation.
Become a Member Your Application Status Journals Journals
Official journals of the British Association of Urological Surgeons.
BJUI JCU Our Staff Workforce Virtual MuseumMuseum Map BAUS Members Art Gallery BAUS Members' Art Gallery
Painting & Drawing (Hall 1) Photography (Hall 2) Sculpture, Pottery & Other Art (Hall 3) Storeroom (Archive) Copyright Advice Submitting Your Artwork Welcome to the Virtual Art Gallery Clubs, Societies and Associates Room Clubs, Societies and Associates' Room
American Association of Genitourinary Surgeons American Urological Association European Association of Urology Punch Club Société Internationale d’Urologie Urological Club of Great Britain & Ireland Diseases & Procedures Room Diseases & Procedures' Room
Bladder Kidneys Prostate Ureters Famous Clinicians Room Famous Clinicians' Room
Arthur Fergusson McGill Arthur Jacobs Charles Phillips Clifford Morson Cuthbert Dukes David Band Edward Canny Ryall Edwin Hurry Fenwick François Gigot de La Peyronie Frank Kidd Frederick Swinford Edwards Horace Winsbury-White Hugh Hampton Young JB ("Jim") Macalpine Joaquín María Albarrán y Domínguez John Blandy John Swift Joly John Wickham Reginald Harrison RHOB ("Joey") Robinson Richard Turner-Warwick Ronald Ogier Ward Sir Eric Riches Sir Francis Cruise Sir Henry Thompson Sir John Thomson-Walker Sir Peter Freyer Terence Millin Thomas Chapman Thomas Hollier Walter Galbraith William Cheselden Willie Mack Hall of Eponyms History of BAUS Room History of BAUS Room
BAUS Annual Meetings BAUS Paraphernalia Presidents of BAUS The BAUS Coat of Arms The Birth of BAUS The British Journal of Urology Training & Academic Urology Hospitals and Institutions Room Hospitals and Institutions' Room
All Saints' Hospital London Norfolk and Norwich Hospital St Paul's Hospital London St Peter's Hospital for Stone London St Phillip's Hospital London Instruments & Equipment Room Instruments & Equipment Room
Aspirators Catheters Cystoscopes Evacuators Lasers Lithotomy Instruments Lithotrites Nephroscopes Prostatic Punches Resectoscopes Urethrotomes & Dilators Urethroscopes Instruments in Other Collections Junior Curators Room Junior Curator's Room
Autograph Cupboard Medal Cabinet Stamp Collection Introduction & Welcome The Bladder Stone Crusher The Junior Curator's Office Videos & Vlogs Library Library
Books & Articles on the History of Urology Books & Articles on Specific Diseases & Procedures Books & Articles on People in Urology Books & Articles on Instruments
BAUS History of Urology Posters Memorial Garden Abdul Mabud Chowdhury Bill Hendry John Anderson Professor Chris Heyns Professor Rob Pickard Richard Turner Warwick CBE Sean Vesey Sir David Innes Williams Other Museum Collections Other Museum Collections
The Bristol (Roger Feneley) Collection The Cambridge (John Withycombe) Collection The Derby (Richard Stanford) Collection The Freeman Hospital (Toby Page) Collection The Leicester (Tim Terry) Donation The Leicester Royal Infirmary Collection The Neath Hospital (Ayman Younis) Collection The Sunderland (Raymond Roy) Collection Standing on the Shoulders of Giants Standing on the Shoulders of Giants
Some "big names" in urology interviewed as part of a living witness programme
Mr John Wickham Mr Richard Turner Warwick Professor John Blandy Sir David Innes Williams Time Corridor Time Corridor
17th Century 18th Century 19th Century Ancient China Ancient Egypt Ancient Greece Ancient India Ancient Israel Arabic Medicine Imperial China Mayan Medicine Medieval Europe Mesopotamia Prehistory Roman Medicine The Dark Ages MyBAUS
BAUS Home
Patients
Surgical Outcomes Audits
Privacy Notice for BAUS Audits
Share
Patients
Surgical Outcomes Audit
Privacy Notice for BAUS Audits
If you would like to make a Subject Access Request for any data about your
operation that is held on the BAUS audits, please complete and return this form
Why the data is collected
BAUS runs a number of national audits and endeavours to collect data from all urologists undertaking the procedures listed below.  The purpose of collecting the data is to monitor the performance of urological surgeons, so that we can improve the outcomes of urological surgery and ensure patient safety. The audits also provide comparative information to patients, commissioners, and regulators of healthcare professionals.
BAUS currently collects data on the following procedures:
Nephrectomy (removal or partial removal of a kidney);
Radical prostatectomy;
Cystectomy (removal of the bladder);
Surgery for female stress urinary incontinence;
Urethroplasty (surgery to repair urethral strictures);
Percutaneous nephrolithotomy, PCNL (the breakdown & removal of kidney stones using a telescope placed into the kidney through a small puncture in the back); and
Penile implant surgery (personal data on penile implant surgery can only be collected if the patient has given explicit consent).
What personal data is collected?
The information entered by the surgeon, or a member of the surgical team, includes the medical history of the disease, the investigations performed, the treatments given and the operative outcomes achieved. The information importantly also contains some personal information about the patient as follows:
Forename
Surname
Gender
NHS number or another identifier such as hospital number
Date of birth
Date of operation
Date of discharge (or death)
Cause of death
PLEASE NOTE:
Date of birth and date of operation generate the age at surgery - required for analysis;
Date of operation and date of discharge (or death) - required to calculate hospital length of stay; and
Date of death and cause of death - required to enable us to report on mortality (for example, it is important to know if the cause of death is related to the surgery).
What is the legal basis for the BAUS Audits?
The collection of data for the BAUS audits has been approved by the Confidentiality Advisory Group of the NHS Health Research Authority under Regulation 5 of the Health Service (Control of Patient Information) Regulations 2002.  The CAG has agreed that “the activity has a clear medical purpose in the publication of audit information around the urological surgical procedures identified, and it was agreed that the activity is important and in the public interest”.
Surgeons are encouraged to seek consent from their patients for their data to be entered on the national registries.  Patients do not have to give consent for personal data to be entered but, if a refusal of consent is recorded, the person entering data cannot enter personal data, although the details of the operation can still be entered. Where a patient has not been asked to consent, their consent is recorded as "unknown" and, in these circumstances, BAUS has permission to collect details for these patients under Section 251 of the NHS Act 2006, in the interests of ensuring patient safety and patient outcomes.
How is the data processed?
Surgeons (or designated members of their teams) add the information to the online BAUS data and audit system using secure data transfer methods.  All data is stored in a secure facility with access controlled by authenticated usernames and passwords. Access is very tightly controlled; clinicians and their teams can only access data about their own patients.
Although BAUS staff can download the surgical data for analysis, they cannot access any patient identifiable data, and all outputs are aggregated so that individual patients cannot be identified.
The information collected is used to generate reports; these are detailed reports which can show national patterns and trends, and allow individual surgeons and units to compare their performance.  Surgeon and unit data is available for the public to view in the Surgical Outcomes Audit section of the BAUS website.  BAUS also shares some aggregated data with the NHS for display on NHS Choices.
Who controls the use of the data?
BAUS is the data controller and is responsible for how the data is used.  The release of any data is subject to rigorous controls and no personal data is released.
Who processes the data?
The data is processed by Dendrite Clinical Systems Ltd.  Their data security policy is fully implemented and complies with current management and control guidelines described in ISO 27001/2 standards. Dendrite Clinical Systems is assessed against NHS Information Governance standards, which includes both physical and organisational security measures.
How long will this information be kept for?
By collecting a large amount of information, it is easier to identify the most effective treatments which can benefit patients.  We hold patient identifiable data dating from 2012, and we anticipate that we will retain these data for at least 10 years to enable us to collect, assess and report on complications, and on outcomes of treatment.  Data retention practices and policy are reviewed on an annual basis.
Patients
COVID-19: Information for PatientsFind a SurgeonGeneral InformationCancerPaediatricsStone Disease Patient Advisory SectionGlossary"I think I might have..."Blood in the semen (haematospermia) Blood in the urine (haematuria) Erectile dysfunction (impotence) Fertility problems Incontinence of urine Kidney stones Male menopause (androgen deficiency in the ageing male) Premature ejaculation Prostate symptoms (bladder outlet obstruction) Raised PSA Testicle missing Testicular lump Tight foreskin (phimosis) Urinary infection (adult) Urinary infection (child) "I'm told I need..."Bladder Procedures Fertility & Infertility Procedures Kidney & Adrenal Procedures Miscellaneous Procedures Penis Procedures Prostate Procedures Retroperitoneum Procedures Stone Procedures Testis & Scrotal Procedures Transplantation & Dialysis Procedures Ureter Procedures Urethra Procedures Surgical Outcomes AuditsInterpretation of the DataUnderstanding the GraphsHow We Do Risk AnalysisGrading of Surgical ComplicationsPrivacy Notice for BAUS AuditsCystectomyAbout the AuditSummary & Timescales of the DataUnderstanding the GraphsNephrectomyAbout the AuditSummary & Timescale of the DataUnderstanding the GraphsPercutaneous Nephrolithotomy (PCNL)About the AuditSummary & Timescale of the DataUnderstanding the GraphsRadical ProstatectomyAbout the AuditSummary & Timescales of the DataUnderstanding the GraphsStress Urinary IncontinenceAbout the AuditSummary & Timescale of the DataUnderstanding the GraphsUrethroplastyAbout the AuditSummary & Timescale of the DataUnderstanding the GraphsVaginal Mesh ComplicationsYour Patient Journey
Print this page
Email to a friend
Link to this page
Add to My Links
Save as PDF
Give feedback
Patients
Professionals
About
Virtual Museum
COVID-19: Information for Patients Find a Surgeon General Information Glossary "I think I might have..." "I'm told I need..." Surgical Outcomes Audits Vaginal Mesh Complications Your Patient Journey
BAUS Business Education & Training Events Regions Specialist Sections Urolink
Contact Us Coronavirus & COVID-19 Find Us (or Hire a Room) Governance & Trustees History of BAUS Joining BAUS Journals Our Staff Workforce
Museum Map BAUS Members Art Gallery Clubs, Societies and Associates Room Diseases & Procedures Room Famous Clinicians Room Hall of Eponyms History of BAUS Room Hospitals and Institutions Room Instruments & Equipment Room Junior Curators Room Library Memorial Garden Other Museum Collections Standing on the Shoulders of Giants Time Corridor
‹
›
×
×
Previous
Next
